EPISODE EIGHT
WE MUST BECOME ICARUS
Excuse me.
We are the ones who posted that problem.
Were you able to solve it
in only half a day?
No, I'm not the one who solved it!
Look, the author is a man.
I'm merely a library assistant.
I posted the reply on my master's behalf.
Oh, I see. I apologize then.
In that case,
could we meet with your master?
Uh, I'm afraid he's not available.
He'll be away for a while!
How long might that be?
A while.
Very well.
I'd like to pass him a message,
but this isn't the place.
If you don't mind,
could you take us somewhere private?
I'll scream over and over
even if I turn into a monster in this dark night
I want to leave it here
this secret.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Slowly eating
the red and blue stars, from the future to the past
one by one
chew them dozens of times and drink when they melt.
Gazing at the starry sky from the hill
this loneliness I feel
by the time my hands are stained
with the dawn's light, I'd have already forgotten it.
This world is conveniently incomplete
so I want to know more
but even if I scream loudly like a monster
it will vanish once more.
Come to think of it,
we haven't introduced ourselves.
My name is Oczy.
Pleased to meet you. My name is Jolenta.
I, uh...
work as Badeni's--
He's my servant.
Huh?
I'm Badeni.
I've been sent by the Central Abbey
to serve as village subdeacon.
You mean that Central Abbey?
Yes. That one.
Wow, I've never met anyone from there.
If I may ask, what is your position
on the problem of universals?
I'm a nominalist. I support Abelard.
I'm also...
Er, my master is also a nominalist.
He supports Ockham.
Ockham is fairly radical, isn't he?
Yes, but the pursuit of truth
requires a certain boldness.
How courageous.
I'm quite impressed.
No, it's nothing like that.
Did you apply that stance
to my problem too?
Yes.
Oh, I mean, that's what my master said!
We're in luck.
We've met the perfect person.
Right.
Her master must be smart
to hire such a clever maid.
Huh? Obviously, she's the author.
What? Really?
She'll be a valuable resource.
She solved that problem in half a day.
Best of all,
we can probably talk to her
without fear of being turned in.
Huh? Why's that?
Because she's a woman.
If she turns us in,
she's likely to be charged as a witch.
A woman works to our advantage.
That's rather cruel!
It's reality.
But I only mean that a woman
is more advantageous than a man.
Whether we tell her or not
remains to be seen.
So, what is your message?
I must say,
your master is a very remarkable man.
Only someone well-versed in astronomy
could solve that problem in half a day.
Do you really think so?
Yes, of course.
Since you're working under such a man,
are you interested in astronomy too?
Huh? Uh, well... a little.
That's wonderful!
Astronomy is a fascinating subject.
I especially enjoy
ancient models of the universe.
How can I put it...
They're so imaginative!
Indeed.
People of long ago
had some fairly astounding ideas.
You could call it free in a way.
Out of curiosity, are you familiar
with the pagan Heraclides?
Yes.
Oh, my! Then what about Philolaus?
He was the one
with that ridiculous theory, right?
Amazing.
You are quite well-informed.
Yes.
As I recall,
the "ridiculous theory" you speak of
was that a mysterious "central fire"
exists at the center of the universe.
Humankind lives on a side of the Earth
where the fire can't be seen.
Meanwhile, the Earth and the Sun
move in circles around the fire.
Um, should we really
be talking about this?
You know...
In terms of faith.
I'm a church official.
Don't be afraid.
Right!
That's a relief.
Philolaus's theory does seem
a bit laughable in this day and age.
I agree.
Creating a model of the universe
where the Earth moves...
It's far too audacious, isn't it?
Yes.
After all, it was God's will
that placed Earth
at the center of the universe.
It's the burden of original sin
and evidence that the Earth
is an unhappy place.
Indeed.
In that case,
have you heard of Aristarchus?
No.
Is that so?
He proposed a theory similar
to the ridiculous one we're discussing.
However, his ideas were a bit different.
Rather than use
subjective reasoning like Philolaus,
his theory was based on observable facts.
What exactly is this about?
Oh, a globe! How rare.
May I touch it?
Yes, go ahead.
Still,
Aristarchus's model
also contained many contradictions,
and it was forgotten.
I'm afraid I don't see
where this is going.
Could we discuss your message?
We are discussing it.
Huh?
What if
the ridiculous theories
of those men were to spread?
There would be chaos!
Their ideas blaspheme against the Church.
It would challenge authority
and all our assumptions.
We couldn't keep the world we have now.
Do you want to keep it the way it is?
What?
What if
we are born with not only sin
but freedom as well?
What would you do
if many of the things we obey and believe,
and the reality we perceive,
are actually lies?
Huh? That's unthinkable.
It defies common sense.
That's true within the bounds
of common sense.
But within the bounds
of these ridiculous theories...
What if our world
really does move?
Huh?
What?!
In that universe, God assigns no classes,
and there is no basis
for enduring despair.
Please stop!
This is improper!
Yes, you're right.
It's improper.
It will never lead us
in the right direction.
We'd have only one thing to pursue.
Truth.
Please...
Please leave.
Very well.
Please tell this to the author.
We'll be waiting
by the bulletin board in the afternoon.
Will this really be okay?
Yeah, it's fine.
One look at her face tells me so.
Because she's a woman?
No.
Because she's a scholar.
The Earth is moving?
That's... the truth?
How terrifying.
How could someone
research something like that?
I've been interested in pagan ideas too,
but the sin of studying them
is on another level.
Oh, no. I have to report this to Kolbe!
At this rate,
I could be charged as a witch
for associating with heretics.
Even so, I have to tell him!
God will never forgive
something like this.
Kolbe!
Oh, they must be at the research meeting.
Count Piast, are you all right?
Yes.
Before we begin, I have something to say.
As I'm sure you're all aware,
I don't have much longer to live.
But before I proceed to heaven,
I am determined to complete
our model of the universe.
At present, humankind is content
with Ptolemy's model.
In truth, it presents few problems
for us in our daily lives.
However,
even if the public accepts it,
we cannot give up the pursuit of truth.
And I cannot believe it is the truth.
The pagans had a myth
about a figure named Icarus.
He flew toward the sun
with wings made of wax
and fell to his death.
His mistake
was not that he had
the arrogance to approach the sun.
It was the ignorance of overlooking
his father's warning that wax would melt.
If wax is not enough,
we must build wings of steel
and continue approaching
that truth we call the sun.
What we lack now
is that audacity.
To complete a true model of the universe,
we must become Icarus.
What are you doing over there?
Count Piast!
I, uh... I was only...
Didn't you apply to do research here?
Yes!
I'm honored that you remember me.
Don't take me for a fool.
I hired you and pay your wages.
Why don't you take part in the meetings?
If it's not worth your time,
I'm happy to fire you.
No, uh, that's...
The chairman and the others
haven't given me permission.
Because you're a woman?
A victim of prejudice, I see.
Then again, they may be right.
What?
I once read a treatise
which stated that demons
often target women for possession.
In addition,
the holy scripture contains passages
that indicate women should
learn quietly, rather than teach.
If that's the case,
it may be fundamentally unsuitable
for women to debate and present ideas.
Is that...
Is that really
the truth?
The holy scripture is the truth.
Yes, of course!
However, we don't know for certain
that we are reading it correctly.
The next time you have
a treatise to present, bring it yourself.
Not to Kolbe. To me.
I won't forgive a tedious work.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
Will she really come?
She will. See for yourself.
What did your master say?
I don't have a master.
Then who wrote this solution?
I did.
Jolenta,
will you assist us?
Yes.
Thank you very much.
In that case--
But first, one thing.
I apologize,
but I am not in a position to freely view
materials about the heavens.
I did so without permission
to solve the problem.
Huh?
However, I do work
at an astronomical laboratory,
so I may be able
to introduce you to a collaborator.
Oh, so that's what you're thinking.
Who will you introduce us to then?
Count Piast.
Count Piast?
Don't tell me you work
at that Count Piast's laboratory.
Yes. That one.
Oczy, let's go.
What?
Jolenta, please forget
everything we've discussed.
What?
Count Piast has access
to every document imaginable.
There is not a more powerful ally.
Listen to yourself!
If you work there, you know
that he'll never cooperate with us!
What is this all about?
Who is Count Piast?
There's only one Piast
in the world of astronomy.
He's a nobleman
who has devoted his entire life
to perfecting the geocentric model.
Count Piast has 50 years
of detailed observation records.
If you miss this opportunity,
heliocentrism will drift out of reach.
Don't be a fool!
Going to Count Piast is too audacious!
Is it more audacious
than moving the Earth?
It's true that Count Piast believes
in the geocentric model more than anyone.
But even more than that,
he believes in truth.
Fine.
In that case, follow me.
Hey, isn't this dangerous?
Don't worry.
If we're arrested,
I'll say we were deceived by a witch.
By utilizing my knowledge,
we can pin most of the charges on her.
This may even work to our advantage.
So you're the ones
who wish to discuss the cosmos?
Yes.
But first, let me say how honored we are--
Forget the stupid flattery!
Get straight to the point.
Recently,
we've been conducting certain research.
One that follows
in Aristarchus's footsteps.
To complete that research,
we would like you to loan us
your observation records.
In addition, this man Oczy
possesses excellent eyesight.
You were once famous
for your eyesight too.
If observation is not
as easy as it once was,
you are free to use Oczy at any time.
I can vouch for the accuracy of--
Leave!
Do you have any idea who I am?
The model you propose
runs counter to the Church's teachings.
Furthermore,
it argues that the research
I've devoted my life to was wrong!
Yes.
But it may be the truth.
Isn't that what you
were really devoted to?
Leave.
We will take our leave for today.
A child of the house of Piast
wishes to study
the lowly field of astronomy?
Father.
Don't bother coming home.
Do you think you can change history
by gazing at the sky?
You're a disgrace to the family name.
Amazing!
This is the Professor's office.
A gold astrolabe?
This is...
It's a one-of-a-kind piece
that I secretly asked an artisan
to make using pagan knowledge.
You're a member
of the Piast family, aren't you?
In terms of bloodline, I--
We're cousins once removed.
I see. That's rather distant.
I was referred here
after declaring an interest in astronomy.
A worthy reason to visit a family outcast.
Now, tell me one thing.
What do you think is most important
for scholarly advancement?
Audacity.
It's precisely because
scholarly research demands caution
that the first step must be a giant leap.
Well said. I like you.
But when it comes to astronomy,
I'm sure everyone opposed you.
Y-Yes.
Let them pinch their useless noses.
They're just spoiled rich folk.
Not true nobility.
But we are different.
We know how to use money appropriately.
What are you researching
in a laboratory this big?
The perfection of the cosmos.
The perfection... of the cosmos?
Our current model contains errors.
Errors in the world God created.
The public may accept it,
but I cannot allow such errors.
That's why I will perfect the model.
I alone will do it.
The massive library of records here
can only be viewed by me.
Eventually, I will reach the truth.
With that in mind,
what is your greatest talent?
What can you contribute to me?
I am able to see great distances.
Oh?
Then show me your observations.
Yes, my lord.
This is...
My lord?
Good!
I give this gold astrolabe to you.
What? B-But...
Isn't this one of a kind?
Superior instruments should be used
by people with superior abilities.
Begin regular observations tomorrow.
Listen, you must not waste
the talent God has given you.
Devote your heart to astronomy.
Then one day, you'll show
those near-sighted fools who doubted you.
By gazing at the sky,
you'll change history.
Show them that you
are the true pride of the family name.
I must perfect the cosmos.
You began to draw
letting out a small sigh
it felt so big.
From the window
rippled beams of light
bounced off your profile.
My body is a gathering of rain
Your fingers are spring's sunlight
filtering through the trees.
The shadows of
ink splashed on paper
depict our profiles.
I had a long dream,
We were in a hot air balloon.
I hope, someone far away
mistook it for the moon.
When I saw the sea,
my soul leapt violently.
You were captivated by the horizon.