Episode Two    And Now…
I'm Going to Move the Earth
If it's the Earth that moves,
reason and beauty become one.
The cosmos is unified
under a single order.
If the theory accepted
by the Church is the geocentric model,
mine is heliocentrism. How about that?
Helio... centrism?
S-Such an idea...
could...
No.
That's just plain wrong.
I'll give you three reasons.
First, there are too many contradictions.
If the Earth is moving...
why do I land in the same spot
when I jump?
Second.
If we accept that the Earth is moving,
who would support that theory?
The Earth is at the center of the universe
because God wanted
humankind's home to be special.
To deny that would be disastrous.
And third.
Risking your life for intuition
is foolish.
A sound argument.
However, I disagree with your third point.
It's because my life is on the line
that I believe my intuition.
And what if you're wrong?
It doesn't matter.
A wrong answer is not a meaningless one.
"A wrong answer is not a meaningless one"?
Are you insane?
I don't find
your heliocentric theory beautiful,
nor will I jump through fire to prove it.
I don't want to come here tomorrow.
Is that so?
Huh?
I'll see you tomorrow then.
The heavens are still,
and the Earth moves?
Not only that,
but it rotates and revolves too?
How could something
that ridiculous be true?
Just look.
Even now,
the stars are moving in small increments.
Watch for an hour, and it's clear.
Even the idea of rotation is impossible.
Man, that hurt!
How clumsy of me.
I thought the mountains
flipped over for a second.
The mountains flipped over?
B-But that's only because
I was moving.
It's not the mountains that moved.
That much is obvious.
But if I extend that obvious logic...
If I'm the Earth,
and the mountains are the Sun...
If the observer moves...
the still object in the distance
will also appear to move.
It may... be rotating.
No, wait!
Even if I accepted the rotation...
there's no way it's revolving.
Let's say Earth moves
for the sake of argument.
I'll apply Ptolemy's model
to the heliocentric theory.
I just need to expand
or shrink the epicyclical radius
of the planets thought to be
beyond the Sun to equal the radius
of the current Sun's revolution.
For planets closer than the Sun,
I'll expand the center
of their epicycles to equal the Sun.
If their induction path
is the same as the current Sun's orbit,
and the Earth followed the same path
as it revolved around the Sun...
This is ridiculous blasphemy.
It's nonsense and plain wrong.
Not only that, I could be arrested.
I have no reason to pursue it.
The individual planets move in sequence,
and the cosmos is unified
under a single order.
Everything moves in a harmonious sequence?
The entire universe moves
under a single order?
It's all lies!
The planets move independently.
That has to be it.
Because if not...
If the vastness of heaven
moved with one mind
in such a rational way...
I can't help but see...
this theory as beautiful!
It may... be true.
I'll scream over and over
even if I turn into a monster in this dark night
I want to leave it here
this secret.
On the Movements of the Earth
Slowly eating
the red and blue stars, from the future to the past
one by one
chew them dozens of times and drink when they melt.
Gazing at the starry sky from the hill
this loneliness I feel
by the time my hands are stained
with the dawn's light, I'd have already forgotten it.
This world is conveniently incomplete
so I want to know more
but even if I scream loudly like a monster
it will vanish once more.
Your observations have grown
even more precise lately.
Did something change?
If I may.
Hu— Hubert,
why put yourself in danger
and give up your place
in heaven just for this?
Do you want to deny the existence of God?
It's the opposite.
I do it because I believe in God.
Most people believe
this world is an ugly place
filled with greed and corruption,
while the afterlife is pure and beautiful.
But
I can't accept that.
This world created by God
is surely the most beautiful of all.
A person doesn't need
faith, money, or status to know that.
I will show
that even trapped in this tiny skull,
my intellect is all I need
to understand God's works.
That's why I don't read
the holy scripture.
I read nature.
But doesn't a life like that...
frighten you?
It does.
Even so,
a life that isn't frightening
is missing its essence.
Oh, and one more thing.
This is your last day of observation.
What?
I've discovered a way to continue alone.
Then what do I do from tomorrow?
Good question.
You're free to choose.
However,
continue astronomy.
For your own sake.
Though that's just a suggestion.
Well, thank you for everything.
It's over.
Just like that.
What was this all about?
"Continue astronomy", he says?
I can't do that.
Potocki?
Why is he in front of the house?
Hi!
Huh?
Hello there.
Are you Rafal?
I'm the Inquisitor, Nowak.
I'm here to inquire
about Hubert's actions since his recantation.
I-Is that so?
Hubert has fully reformed,
and he's been living modestly.
Oh? I'm glad to hear that.
After all, a man charged
as a heretic twice will be put to death.
His collaborators
would face serious charges too.
All that extra work
is no fun for me either.
Th-That sounds rough.
I can't tolerate those foolish heretics.
Glad to have your support.
So tell me then...
What's this?
I found it in your bookcase.
I haven't told Potocki yet,
but it sure seems to contain
detailed notes about blasphemous research.
What is this?
It's... uh...
What could it be?
That belongs to me.
H-Hubert?!
I thought it would be harder to find
if I hid it in that child's room,
but it seems I've been caught.
Oh? So that's the case, is it?
But you'd better think carefully, Hubert.
Do you realize
where such a statement will lead you?
I came back to finish what I started.
Be honest, please.
Does this really belong to you?
Of course it does.
In fact, you're the one
who should think carefully.
Do you really think
a child could assist with my research?
Well, I suppose that's true.
Sorry about that, Rafal.
In that case, put Hubert under arrest.
Huh?
Wait!
So suddenly?!
Oh, that's right.
I came to give you this.
Farewell.
Huh?
Hubert!
Will you really just go?
Weren't you going to finish something?
I just did.
And so, Hubert
was burned to death.
Orb
On the Movements of the Earth
He died.
To save me.
I know he was a heretic,
but what was the right thing for me to do?
His unfinished work...
Three stars.
Orion's Belt?
Why is only Alnilam
in the center painted black?
I'm fond of the way
those mountains
and rocks resemble Orion's Belt.
Wait!
I've come to the mountain
that represents Alnilam,
but I don't see-
This is
a letter?
"To the person who finds this letter."
Please forgive the curt opening,
but I have no idea who you are.
However, I have decided
to entrust my necklace
to the one I deem most trustworthy.
Now to the main order of business.
The documents you see here
comprise my lifetime of research
into heliocentrism.
I now place all my trust in you
and beg you to finish what I started.
Please,
burn everything.
I am confident that I have spent more time
with heliocentrism than anyone else.
Because of that,
there is something I alone know.
Heliocentrism can likely never be proven.
There are too many uncertain factors.
It surely must be
the realm of God himself.
If that is the case,
such an imperfect theory should disappear.
Despite that, I don't have the will
or the courage to burn it myself.
Instead, it is my selfish hope
that someone superior to me
will dispose of it forever.
That is you.
You are capable of burning it.
Your powers of reason
are far stronger than my intuition.
You can do it.
A reward for the task
can be found in the box.
The amount should be sufficient.
And so, I leave it to you.
Well, it is what it is.
I understand why he chose
to leave this letter too.
Heliocentrism is indeed an amazing idea.
But it's too dangerous,
too out of step with the times,
and more than anything else, too uncertain.
This is the most reasonable outcome.
The materials must be burned.
It's just as Hubert said.
My powers of reason
set the documents aflame.
But...
Ow!
More than that reasoning,
my intuition wants to
believe in heliocentrism!
Everyone, listen up!
While we're sorry to see him go,
today is the day Rafal leaves our school!
However,
he'll be attending university.
And everyone,
what is the
most appropriate field for him to study?
Do you remember?
Theology!
That's right.
Rafal, do you have any parting words?
Yes.
Thank you for all you've done for me.
We won't see each other anymore,
but I pray that
you receive God's blessings.
Oh, and one more thing.
I'm going to study astronomy.
Though it pains me to say it,
the world is full of fools.
And before I knew it,
I was at the head of the line.
The real me
is neither dignified,
nor wise, humble, or capable.
What I am is arrogant, brazen,
rash, and helpless.
And now... I'm going to move the Earth.
If you need help, just ask an adult.
See? Just like that.
Here you go.
Thank you very much!
I can't just ignore a crying child.
Be good to your family, okay?
Yes, sir!
Nowak, we'd better get moving.
Huh? Oh, right.
I hope you'll forgive the sudden visit.
What do you intend to do?
I have a child!
Oh, is that so?
I have a daughter myself.
She just turned four,
and she's quite cute.
Look, this is a letter from my daughter.
I always carry it with me.
Whenever I think of her,
I get the same feelings.
Comfort, strength, and...
worry.
Love for my child
has become my reason to live.
I don't ever want her to suffer.
So any research that will disrupt
the peace can't be overlooked.
To tell the truth, I don't have
any lofty ideals like protecting humanity.
But when it comes to
protecting the lives and faith
of my family and friends,
there's nothing I won't do.
I'm home!
Oh, my.
So this was your family.
Okay, this is where the wicked gather.
I'll leave the rest to you.
I have dinner with my family to get to.
Huh?
Aren't inquisitors celibate too?
You didn't know?
Nowak never joined the clergy.
He's a layperson.
I don't know the details,
but the Bishop thinks highly of him
and made an exception.
He was once a mercenary.
A mercenary?
How could such bloody hands
do the Lord's work?
It's unthinkable.
How could this be?
Don't get so disheartened.
I'm sure the Bishop has his reasons.
You must
be joking.
You're joking, right?
Huh?
Not only are you abandoning theology,
but it's to study astronomy?
Has Hubert being arrested as a heretic
momentarily robbed you of your senses?
If you don't retract that statement,
I won't sign
this university admission form!
Recently,
after my sudden change in direction,
my future has grown quite precarious.
Being honest,
skillfully explaining myself,
and settling all concerns
would be a Herculean task.
Now, declare it!
You won't study astronomy!
And so...
Understood. I declare it.
I'll never study astronomy again.
I simply lied.
Oh, my son!
You've returned to your normal self?
Yes! I was being a fool!
I'm so happy!
One can express anything in words.
That's why lying is so convenient.
The rational judgment I've developed
can help me avoid trouble.
Right. That's the way.
Even if I enroll in theology,
I can transfer to astronomy later.
Not going to university
would defeat the purpose.
Proving heliocentrism
could take 30 or 40 years.
But even then, it's no pipe dream.
I just need to proceed little by little.
Still,
if my father hates astronomy so much,
why are there so many
books on it inside this house?
You began to draw
letting out a small sigh
it felt so big.
From the window
rippled beams of light
bounced off your profile.
My body is a gathering of rain
Your fingers are spring's sunlight
filtering through the trees.
The shadows of
ink splashed on paper
depict our profiles.
I had a long dream,
We were in a hot air balloon.
I hope, someone far away
mistook it for the moon.
When I saw the sea,
my soul leapt violently.
You were captivated by the horizon.
Brought to you by [KawaSubs]