These are all our supplies.
I'll take a sword.
Okay, Draka. Let's go.
Are you all okay with this?
It's our duty.
Preferences don't matter.
We only just met.
I don't know any of you,
and you don't know me.
However, we all knew Jolenta.
She promised to loan me
the printing press.
It's up to you
to find something new to sell.
Not a bad deal, I'd say.
Well?
She only said that so I would tell her
the contents of the book.
From her perspective,
it may not have meant much.
But to me,
her voice sounded as if
she was encouraging my way of life
and my future.
I'm sure all of you are here
because, at some moment,
you too felt something like that
from Jolenta and this organization.
So, what I'm trying to say is…
I'll do my duty too.
Good. We're counting on you.
Right.
I'll scream over and over
even if I turn into a monster in this dark night
I want to leave it here
this secret.
On the Movements of the Earth
Slowly eating
the red and blue stars, from the future to the past
one by one
chew them dozens of times and drink when they melt.
Gazing at the starry sky from the hill
this loneliness I feel
by the time my hands are stained
with the dawn's light, I'd have already forgotten it.
This world is conveniently incomplete
so I want to know more
but even if I scream loudly like a monster
it will vanish once more.
Episode Twenty Two      Neither Of You Will Be Known To History
Huh?
What is it?
I can't get that explosion out of my head.
Our enemy
must be willing
to do anything for their cause.
I'm… scared.
In just a few hours,
morning will come, as it always does.
I hope one day
you too will learn to smile
at the sunrise.
That again?
I told you. I hate the sunrise.
I'd appreciate it
if you didn't repeat yourself.
It's annoying.
I'm not merely repeating myself.
This time, I mean it.
What? You mean it?
Are you trying to irritate me?
Interpret it however you like,
but it's an expression of my gratitude.
Even if the sunrise means nothing to you,
to me, it's the most wonderful moment
a person can experience.
I wanted to share that with you.
But… why?
Who knows?
However, it's probably because
you and I happened to cross paths.
It's awfully quiet.
I… I'm an inquisitor!
You know why we're here!
Surrender quietly!
Fire!
The testudo formation, huh?
Don't panic.
That formation is vulnerable
to close combat.
-We just--
-Charge!
-Engage them in close combat!
-Yes, sir!
Here they come!
Now!
Attack their right flank more!
Hey!
Damn it. These guys are decoys.
Unhook the carts and take only the horses!
Asch!
Huh? Uh, I… Not me.
Well, I suppose it is my job.
I leave this mess to you.
Damn it. They're gaining on us!
Yes. So it seems.
What do we do?
I've never been afraid
to carry out a decision I made.
What?
That's because
I always thought I was simply obeying
the destiny God gave me.
But right now,
I'm afraid for the first time.
Huh?
I pray for your success!
Schmidt!
I've killed many of your comrades.
Faith was my motive.
But right now,
my faith is wavering.
The justification I once had
for killing you
is no more.
But even so, I'm going to kill you
for my own selfish reasons.
Forgive me!
What are you babbling about?
Wretched heretic!
Die!
Burn in hell!
He's choking to death on his own blood.
It's just the sort of miserable death
a believer in heliocentrism deserves.
Even… so…
it's the fate… I… chose.
Who are you?
Why are you here at this hour?
I'm a tinsmith.
Oh? Where's your authorization?
It's these.
Bishop!
What is it?
You better have a good reason
to disturb my sleep.
You have a visitor.
Apparently, it's important.
What sort of visitor?
A woman.
From her clothing,
she appears to be a nomad.
I had a feeling it was you.
It's been a while.
What did you want to speak about?
The future.
Something… profitable.
-Leave us alone.
-Huh?
This is for my ears.
Footprints…
Something profitable, huh?
I'm intrigued.
And? What's your idea?
I'll cut straight to the point.
It's a book.
In the future,
as personal property ownership spreads,
I think books will sell well.
Right now, the people desire pleasure
more than religion.
From street performances
to public executions,
you've seen the way
they gather like vultures.
Everyone is starving for stimulation.
That's where books come in.
The written word
can reach the brain directly.
If it becomes easy for people to read,
they'll grow addicted.
You can read anywhere,
and at any time too.
Mass printing with movable type is cheap
and frighteningly easy.
If it catches on,
the profits could be immense.
That's where I'd like your cooperation.
I need access to a printing press
and permission to publish.
I won't let them go to waste.
Yeah?
Okay, so what's the book about?
That's the complicated part.
Huh?
It's a sort of cosmological model,
or a certain hypothesis
about nature, you could say.
To put it simply,
it's about the movements of the Earth.
Are you… What are you--
Do you think it's blasphemy?
Even so,
I have more to say.
Please think about it.
Have you ever heard
of a historical precedent
for heliocentrism being suppressed?
Is heliocentrism
really blasphemy?
What? Of course it is.
Spare me the jokes.
Well, this was a waste of time.
Before I send you to the dungeon,
I'll let you in on something.
My father sentenced many people
to death for heliocentrism in the past.
To continue its suppression, he…
Wait.
When you put it that way,
I've never heard of it
being suppressed elsewhere.
I knew it!
The words create an impression,
and everyone avoids it out of fear.
When I first learned of it,
I thought it sounded dangerous too.
After all, cosmology
runs counter to divine creation.
Avoiding it seems obvious.
You could be punished for that,
and one has to be careful.
But… But then…
As long as you're careful,
is there any reason
it should be absolutely forbidden?
And couldn't it be
a subject that stimulates enjoyment?
In other words, you believe
that whether heliocentrism is blasphemy
could change at the discretion
of whoever is in power at the time?
Yes. Exactly.
Very well.
But you should understand this.
If the winds shift against us,
I'll cut you off with no second thoughts.
Then that means--
Slow down.
We haven't talked about the profit ratio.
Fifty-fifty.
You must be kidding.
Consider the compromise I'm making.
Eighty-twenty.
Understood.
Then I'll be going.
That should settle everything.
Th-Thank you very much!
-One more thing.
-Huh?
To commemorate the publishing,
there's a letter I'd like to send.
Do you mind?
In that case, use my carrier pigeon.
I'll summon for it now.
Who goes there?
I'm cooperating
with a heretic investigation.
Here is my authorization.
I followed my suspect's footprints here.
Has anyone suspicious come around?
- Actually, there was a woman just now.
- A woman?
Which way did she go?
Huh?
Toward the church.
The church?
Is there a place near here
where I can get a stiff drink?
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
-Huh?
What?
Y-You're…
Bishop Antoni?
Is this where you serve as bishop?
It's me, Nowak!
I once served as an inquisitor.
Yes, I remember.
P-Please step away from that woman!
You're in danger!
She's a heretic!
She believes…
in that accursed heliocentric theory.
And?
A… "And"?
I said heliocentrism!
The same theory that
your father was so wary of…
You must remember!
So please step away from her…
Huh?
W-What's going on?
Why have you gone quiet?
No… It can't be.
You can't be serious.
Don't tell me you and that heretic…
Just tell me one thing.
What is your understanding
of the problem with heliocentrism?
What?
Th-That's…
Cosmology touches upon divine creation.
The details are…
Well…
The previous Bishop said--
Quite vague, wouldn't you say?
Listen, Nowak.
If you fail to understand,
then I'll be clear.
If you're going to label, torture,
and kill people as heretics,
you should learn for yourself
whether such steps are justified.
Take responsibility for your actions.
Justified? But…
Th-That's right. The Holy Scripture says…
"You established the earth,
and it endures."
Or perhaps,
"The world is firmly established;
it cannot be moved."
Are those the verses that come to mind?
Well, if you stop and think clearly,
those verses aren't enough to prove
that heliocentrism is blasphemy.
That's because
even heliocentrism is just
one hypothesis among many.
Perhaps it's too uncertain
to call it the one and only truth,
but in the end, it's merely
a mathematical postulate.
What in the world is wrong with that?
In fact,
even if it were proven
that the Earth is moving,
rereading the Holy Scripture
with that in mind
and providing the proper interpretation
is our work as theologians.
Rather than reject
new opinions or discoveries,
we must explore them
to better understand the Holy Scripture.
Isn't that stance
what our faith needs the most now?
On the contrary,
placing the Sun
at the center of the universe
could be seen as natural scientific proof
of the Holy Trinity.
From a theological perspective,
it could be a wonderful discovery
that reveals God's glory.
B-But…
Your father…
Yes.
My father was strict about cosmology.
I don't know the reason,
but as I'm sure you're aware,
he once studied astronomy too.
While doing so,
perhaps he experienced some setback
that changed his reverence for the heavens
into an inferiority complex.
Either way,
I imagine the story
goes something like this.
Somewhere in the world,
there was an authority
who had a strict view of cosmology.
Scholars researching heliocentrism
had the misfortune of serving under him
and were branded as heretics.
People then began to believe the myth
that heliocentrism was a forbidden topic.
The dirty work of that operation
could not be entrusted
to an inquisitor from the clergy.
It was contracted out.
In other words, it was entrusted to you,
a former mercenary.
If that's what happened,
this entire scandal was not a crusade
to protect the Church or the faithful.
It was merely a misunderstanding
created by a small group of people.
A misunderstanding?
How can you pass this off
as just a misunderstanding?!
Hubert, Rafal, Oczy, Badeni!
These men were executed
for researching heliocentrism,
and they were killed by me!
N-Not to mention…
my daughter…
That's right, the records!
There are records--
None of the executions were made public.
Besides, it was more than 25 years ago.
Who knows if the records remain?
Looking back, it was strange.
Far too many of your cosmology executions
were filed away as confidential.
Still, I'm a cautious man.
Just now, I ordered my men
to look up your remaining records
and destroy any that were found.
By tomorrow morning, they'll all be gone.
Was I really…
Was I really the only one?
In all the world, the only one…
who actually suppressed
heliocentrism was me?
Yes.
To the best of my knowledge.
After all this time… you expect me to…
Had we been born elsewhere,
or at another time,
there were other possibilities.
However, that is not the case.
That's what we call fate.
It's unfortunate,
but you'll have to accept it.
When it comes to you
and the heretics you executed…
neither of you will be known to history.
I saw that wandering cloud
My scales resembled you
Below were two of my sleepless eyelids
tsu,
And a faint scent of mugwort lingered
Under that wandering cloud
My heart resembled embers
Shoes unnecessary, ears unaware
I listened to the sound of your breathing
I slid off the bed of bluebells
It felt like spring
Is that how the titmouse sings?
Unfamiliar with the sea, cherishing flowers
And gazing at the sky
I still want to see the clouds of Mt. Wushan
Brought to you by [KawaSubs]