Hey, you two.
Hello there.
I'm Nowak. I'll be training you.
Pleased to meet you.
Th-The pleasure is ours.
Nervous, huh?
I get it.
Our work is socially necessary,
but dealing with heretics,
let alone torturing them,
certainly isn't pleasant.
I haven't even told my daughter
what I really do.
But don't worry.
You'll get used to it.
Anyway, the thing
you should be most prepared for
is this.
Any idea what this could be?
Uh...
No.
This is the amount of paperwork required
to close even one heretic's case.
In other words,
this work can be a real pain.
But then, what you really want to know
is how to move up
the ladder efficiently, right?
Huh?
Here's how I approach things.
The Bishop is especially concerned
with theories of the cosmos.
If you volunteer for a case like that,
you'll earn points with him.
Also, rather than spending
lots of time on a major target,
take care of smaller ones
in large numbers.
Greater numbers
will earn you a good reputation.
Any questions?
U-Um,
why is the Bishop
concerned with the cosmos?
Oh...
Well, you see,
the Bishop once studied astronomy.
Huh?!
Despite that,
he's practically allergic to it now.
When that happens,
it usually points to trouble long ago.
Your young experiences
tend to stick with you.
Any more questions?
In that case, we'll continue
in the inquisition chamber.
Let's go.
Oh, hello there, Antoni.
I thought I heard a racket.
What are you inquisitors doing here?
Well...
The Bishop wanted to encourage
the new recruits.
Recruits?
Give me a break.
You inquisitors are costing us
enough money already.
Now you're hiring new recruits?
Now, now. A clergyman
needn't fret over money, right?
Ignorant as always.
Listen to me.
Whether it's fighting holy wars
or maintaining the Church,
they both require money.
It's time you learned
what money is really worth.
I don't know how you earned
the Bishop's favor,
but an inquisitor should know his place.
Gotcha.
Will do.
The Bishop's stupidity knows no bounds.
Who was that?
He's a curate, maybe?
I don't know his official title.
To put it more simply,
he's the Bishop's son.
His son? Isn't he celibate?
Of course he is.
In public anyway.
Now then, let's change gears
and head to the inquisition chamber.
I'll scream over and over
even if I turn into a monster in this dark night
I want to leave it here
this secret.
On the Movements of the Earth
Slowly eating
the red and blue stars, from the future to the past
one by one
chew them dozens of times and drink when they melt.
Gazing at the starry sky from the hill
this loneliness I feel
by the time my hands are stained
with the dawn's light, I'd have already forgotten it.
This world is conveniently incomplete
so I want to know more
but even if I scream loudly like a monster
it will vanish once more.
Episode Eleven    『 Terror 』
Oh, that's right.
Before we go in, I have a question.
Have either of you
ever talked to a heretic?
N-No.
Of course not.
That figures.
Well, there's just one thing
to be careful of.
They're skillful liars.
Don't be fooled.
A w-woman?
Yes.
A lot of them are, you know.
She was only arrested yesterday.
She says she knows nothing
about the black mass.
But we got tips from multiple sources,
so we have to investigate thoroughly.
Your task for today
is to learn the basics.
The thumb screw.
Wakey-wakey.
Good morning.
As I asked you yesterday,
please tell us about the black mass.
I also need you to reveal
your collaborators.
I've told you again and again!
I don't know anything!
Put this around her thumb.
Huh?
H-Hey!
So, do you have anything to say now?
I told you. I don't know anything!
Turn it.
Huh?
Now.
We know you went
in and out of those woods.
Who told you about that place?
You must have a collaborator.
Don't you want this to be over
as much as me?
I told you...
I was only out foraging,
and I ended up in those woods.
You leave me no choice.
Turn it again.
B-But any further and—
Do it.
That's what our instructions call for.
We can't close the case otherwise.
Okay, you can take it off.
You're next.
There's still the left hand.
Please... stop this.
Then talk.
There's no way you arrived
at those woods by chance.
Someone told you.
Why?
Why is this happening to me?
Turn it.
What if she really doesn't know anything?
Do it.
G-God, please.
I can't.
Oh? I see.
That's understandable.
You did well.
In that case, back to you.
Hurry up.
P-Please stop!
I'll talk!
My neighbor Anna told me!
My younger brother is ill,
and she said I could get herbs
at the black mass.
I'm not... a witch.
I only wanted medicine.
I never thought this would happen.
I'm sorry, Anna.
Please forgive me.
Thank you for the information.
Okay, let's take a break.
I'm very sorry for what I did.
It's fine.
I get why it's hard. It's your first day.
Still, if you want to finish work early,
you'll need a change of heart.
But is this really the right way?
They might lie
to escape the pain.
Couldn't we try dialog a bit more?
God's love can—
The answer is no.
Listen.
We have no authority in the first place.
Our role is to do as we're told.
Plus, if there's one thing I've learned,
it's that heretics
will do whatever it takes.
They have a pact with the devil
to change the world.
Do you know what's most important
to prevent that and maintain
the world we have now?
Orb
On the Movements of the Earth
Terror
It's terror.
Terror?
Nowak!
Huh?
You've received
an emergency dispatch order!
A tip came in.
What? Why do I have to go?
I'm in the middle
of training these recruits.
You were named personally by the Bishop.
Then I guess I have no choice.
You'll have to hear the rest
from someone else.
See you around.
What is it this time? The cosmos again?
So it seems.
Forgive me.
You had to torture her in my place.
Well, you do owe me one.
Right. Thanks.
That man...
He wasn't fazed at all.
If we do this long enough,
will we get used to it like him?
Who knows.
Either way, we have to go on.
For the sake of
humankind.
Huh?
It's me, Oczy!
It's almost the appointed time.
We should begin heading toward town!
Got it! I just need to write this letter.
Well, it can wait.
I'll do it later.
It's been a while!
Yes, it has, Jolenta.
Hello.
Well then... Cheers!
Cheers!
By the way,
if I may ask,
have you made progress?
Yes.
That's why I called you both here today.
It's finished.
You mean it?
Well, to be precise,
it's developed to the point
where I don't mind making it public.
Then that means even now...
Yes.
Right now...
as we speak...
in this very moment...
we're moving.
Still, it's strange
to think that we're the only ones
who know the truth.
Yeah, I can barely believe it.
Neither can I.
Huh?
While the mathematical explanation
of planetary orbits is complete,
there is much left to explain
in terms of natural philosophy.
Addressing those puzzles is next.
About that.
What will you do from now on?
Once I complete my final preparations,
I'll head to a republic in the southwest.
I've heard they have
more freedom to research there.
Besides,
the Abbot from the Central Abbey
is spreading bad rumors about me.
I'll give up the cloth
and hide among the secular.
I have no further need
for the clergy anyway.
To support myself, I'll work as a tutor
for nobles or the wealthy
interested in academics.
Once that groundwork is laid,
I'll look for a chance to publish.
So you're leaving the village then?
Yes.
Did you know that, Oczy?
Though he only told me recently.
Once Badeni leaves,
I'm planning to go to another city.
A city?
Yes.
I'll find work somewhere
and save money for a few years.
Eventually, I'm thinking
of going to university.
What?
I've developed an interest.
I have no set plans for the future.
I thought I'd give it a try.
Seriously?
I think it's a wonderful goal!
Please do your best!
And you, Jolenta? What about your future?
My superior Kolbe was promoted,
and he recruited me to join
the new astronomy research team.
I'll work there for the time being.
Eventually,
I'd like to publish a treatise
in my own name.
Your own name?
Yes.
Right now, I can't mention my name at all.
But if I can create a precedent,
it might be easier for those after me.
Someday, there may be a future
and an environment
where everyone is equally free to study.
If I could help build that...
Oh, but that's just a dream for now.
A dream?
Oh, uh... my guild mentor used to say
that it's good to have dreams.
These days, I feel like
I finally understand what he meant.
As long as I have a dream,
I feel like I can survive
a week's worth of tragedy.
That's definitely valuable.
Yes, I agree.
Oh, that reminds me.
What happened to the book
you've been writing, Oczy?
Actually, I finished it a short while ago.
Really? I'd love to read it!
Oh, but it's not meant for an audience.
I only wrote it to organize my thoughts.
That won't do.
When you put something in words,
it's a shame not to share it!
Hello there, Jolenta.
Huh?! What are you doing here?
I was in the area for work,
so I thought I'd surprise you.
I asked your coworkers where to find you.
Is that so?
You surprised me.
Oh, excuse me, everyone.
I didn't mean to interrupt.
Sorry. I'll introduce you.
This is my father.
Hello. I'm Jolenta's father, Nowak.
Forgive me, but may I sit down?
Of course. Go ahead.
B-By the way,
what sort of work do you do, sir?
That's, uh...
Let's just say I help the Church.
As you can see,
he never tells me the details.
When a man's with his family,
he wants to forget about work.
You don't have to hold back.
After all, you're serving God, right?
Let's just say it's complicated.
I-Is that so?
If I may...
How do you two know my daughter?
You don't seem to be associated
with Count Piast's laboratory.
That's, uh...
As you can tell from my appearance,
we work at the village church.
In that case, you probably
shouldn't drink too much!
We also conduct research
into astronomy and astrology on the side.
Research?
A short time ago,
we met your daughter
at the town bulletin board.
She's very well-informed,
so we meet once in a while
to exchange knowledge.
Oh?
How magnificent!
I'm so moved, I was at a loss for words.
Huh?
You're a clergyman and a scholar too?
You must be quite diligent.
I'm embarrassed to say so,
but I have a bit of a lazy streak.
Not at all.
My diligence is nothing
compared to your daughter's.
She's a clearheaded and wise person.
Huh?
Well...
Thank you very much!
To be honest, hearing those words
is one of the happiest moments of my life.
Come on, don't be melodramatic.
It's embarrassing.
Can't a father be happy
when his daughter is praised?
A little more humility wouldn't hurt.
Well then, this is where we part.
I apologize for his sudden appearance.
Not at all.
Let's meet again sometime.
Huh?
We...
We're safe!
What's the matter with you?
You've been acting strange.
Is this another weird commoner thing?
It's nothing like that!
Just now,
I was in the greatest danger of my life!
What?
Not long ago,
I met Jolenta's father somewhere.
And if my memory is correct, he's—
Do you two have a moment?
Hello there.
Didn't you leave with Jolenta?
I sent my daughter back alone.
I still have work to do.
Work?
The truth is
I'm an inquisitor.
You began to draw
letting out a small sigh
it felt so big.
From the window
rippled beams of light
bounced off your profile.
My body is a gathering of rain
Your fingers are spring's sunlight
filtering through the trees.
The shadows of
ink splashed on paper
depict our profiles.
I had a long dream,
We were in a hot air balloon.
I hope, someone far away
mistook it for the moon.
When I saw the sea,
my soul leapt violently.
You were captivated by the horizon.
Brought to you by [KawaSubs]