You're not prepared to die, are you?
We're about to find out.
Well, this is a dilemma.
You were prepared to die after all.
Yes! I guess so!
It's probably because
the fear of death is nothing
compared to the fear
of placing hope in this world!
I thought I was gonna die.
Sorry, we're late! Are you all right?
He's still breathing.
Get him to a doctor immediately.
We need to interrogate him.
Don't let him die no matter what.
I'll scream over and over
even if I turn into a monster in this dark night
I want to leave it here
this secret.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Slowly eating
the red and blue stars, from the future to the past
one by one
chew them dozens of times and drink when they melt.
Gazing at the starry sky from the hill
this loneliness I feel
by the time my hands are stained
with the dawn's light, I'd have already forgotten it.
This world is conveniently incomplete
so I want to know more
but even if I scream loudly like a monster
it will vanish once more.
EPISODE 13
FREEDOM
What are you doing, Oczy?
What?
Class is over.
Huh?
This is...
What am I doing here?
Was my class so boring
that you've forgotten it already?
Huh? No, uh...
What is it? You're acting strange.
Somehow,
I feel as if I've been having
a strange dream.
What sort of dream?
I was researching something.
Something dangerous.
Heliocentrism, maybe?
Huh?
How did you know?
That's the subject
of your research, isn't it?
But that can't be made public!
If you don't make it public,
how can anyone debate it?
Shall we talk outside?
What is this place?
Don't be silly.
It's the tower!
Soon, we'll reach the heavens.
You know,
I still have trouble believing
that this earth we stand upon is round.
When the tower is finished,
we'll look down
on the Earth with our own eyes.
Its shape, its color,
even its size...
We'll perceive it all.
What could be more exciting?
Is it okay to build something like this?
Whether it's okay or not,
there's no way to stop it.
Huh?
Why did you choose to study heliocentrism?
I think it was because
I wanted to have hope in this world.
Oh?
So that's how you've perceived it.
However, that's just
the superficial reason you created.
In truth,
you're pursuing a grander ideal.
No, you're driven by it.
One could say that
you're a servant of that ideal.
Then again, you yourself
are not mindful of that ideal.
You believe it to be
something you'll never have.
Still,
humans naturally long for it.
We are built to desire such a thing.
And that desire
is one of the few things about humans
that I believe is worthy of respect.
What are you trying to say?
What grand ideal?
What is driving me?
The only one who can answer that is you.
Huh?
There is something you've longed for
from the bottom of your heart.
It's time you realized it.
What a surprise!
You really woke up.
Be grateful to the doctor.
He saved your life.
You probably survived
because of the soup he fed you.
Huh?
Where am I?
I guess the confusion is natural.
This is the medical area
inside the inquisition chamber.
You've been sleeping here for a week.
A week?
You have one strong will to live.
Although the medicine surely helped.
Why?
Huh?
Why did you keep me alive?
You'll only kill me later.
You've got the wrong idea.
My job is to get you to talk.
You're only good to me alive.
You may be sentenced to death,
but it's not our job to carry it out.
You won't die while my work is underway.
But of course, you will die afterward.
You're no mere heretic.
You committed an armed assault against us.
Could you leave the two of us alone?
Very well.
Say...
This is a personal question.
There's something on my mind,
and I'd like to ask before we begin.
It's always been a mystery to me.
Why do heretics keep appearing?
I mean, it makes no sense.
God made us a promise.
If we live a good and quiet life,
we can go to heaven.
Why would you deliberately give that up?
I could understand
if the devil has driven you mad.
But having spoken with heretics,
I know it's not that simple.
Some of them are of sound mind.
What were you thinking?
What motivates you?
If demonic possession isn't the reason,
why do you heretics exist?
I couldn't tell you.
But... in my case,
I think it's because
I made the mistake
of longing for and seeking something.
What did you seek?
What grand ideal?
What is driving me?
The only one who can answer that is you.
Freedom.
I guess I'll never understand.
"Freedom" sounds good and all,
but without a code of law,
we're no different from beasts.
Yes. You may be right.
But if we can't question that code,
that's no different from beasts either.
Doesn't common sense tell you
that you've gone too far?
Just because you believe that
the sun is the center of the universe,
you killed three of my men.
Talk about blind faith.
I tried to avoid their vital spots.
They died, did they?
We each fought for our convictions.
They must have been ready.
Well, either way...
There's nothing more for me to say.
Because I don't know anything.
Excuse me!
Huh?
Um, can I ask what you've done
with the stone chest since then?
I've finished my book,
and I'd hoped to store it in there.
I threw the stone chest down a ravine
and burned all the documents inside.
We have Count Piast's
perfect observation records anyway.
That chest is useless now.
So you finished your book?
Show it to me.
R-Right.
It may be finished,
but I'm sure there are mistakes.
If you have any advice...
Huh?
Wait, what?!
Hey!
How could you do that?
I could ask you the same thing.
It's too dangerous to leave this.
I told you I would burn it.
In fact,
I think you should be grateful
that I overlooked this until now.
All evidence should obviously be burned.
I have a simple question.
If we do happen to be caught,
they might torture us
until we hand over our materials.
If all the evidence is destroyed,
we won't have anything
to hand over, right?
Even if we tell the truth
and say that we burned all the evidence,
will they believe us?
We can't prove that everything is gone,
so the torture will continue.
What do we do then?
That's obvious.
We simply accept
the nightmare that confronts us.
Um, are we finished?
I really don't know a thing.
Do you know the essence of torture?
It's simple, really.
You weigh bargaining chips on a scale
with the target's convictions.
Most of the time, that means weighing
their desire to not reveal information
against the bargaining chip
of ending the pain by disclosing it.
That gets most people to talk.
But sometimes, you get someone strange.
I don't know if they have a death wish
or they've simply lost their senses,
but they withstand the pain.
Normal methods of torture
don't work against those people.
In those cases, you need
more effective bargaining chips.
For example, the threat of inflicting pain
on their family, friends,
or collaborators.
I can't tell you what I don't know.
No matter what chips you use.
You don't get it.
You're the bargaining chip.
Huh?
Bring him in.
He'll tell us what we need to know.
ORB: ON THE MOVEMENTS OF THE EARTH
Orb.
Now then...
All the players are here.
Remove the blindfold.
H-How did...
You didn't seriously think
he would get away?
He's one of us after all.
As you've probably noticed by now,
in this world,
enemies of the one true church
have nowhere to run.
Now then, let's get started.
Badeni,
please do us the favor
of answering honestly.
Otherwise, there will be suffering.
Do you commune with the devil?
No.
Oh, is that so?
Have you ever attended a black mass?
No.
The next question is an important one.
With regard to your research,
do you have collaborators?
If we're arrested,
I'll say we were deceived by a witch.
None.
I see.
Okay, I'd say we're warmed up now.
To be honest, those questions
were the ones I was required to ask.
What I really want you to answer
is the next one.
What is it you want to know?
Before I get to that,
I owe you both thanks.
I'm embarrassed to say it,
but because of you,
I've become aware of my mistakes,
and I'm ready to correct them.
I've been negligent
in dealing with you people.
And it's not that I've lacked
opportunities to change.
In fact, I had a glaringly obvious chance.
It was just too strange to process.
Instead, I turned away, forgot about it,
and avoided making changes.
Because of that error,
I allowed you heretics
to commit the barbaric act
of approaching my beloved daughter.
I had opportunities to stop you.
Ten years ago,
I was assigned the case
of a certain heretic.
That necklace you have belonged to him.
I don't know how,
but it crossed time and space
to enter your hands.
Ten years ago,
if I had been more diligent in my work,
I could have prevented all of this.
As a parent, there is no greater shame.
So again, I thank you both.
My eyes are finally open.
Now to the point.
You two inherited
that research from somewhere.
That means the materials
still exist somewhere now.
We can't prove that everything is gone,
so the torture will continue.
What do we do then?
That's obvious.
We simply accept
the nightmare that confronts us.
Well? Answer me.
It's true that we inherited the research.
Then tell me--
However...
You seem to be operating
from a fundamental misunderstanding.
I have no interest
in honoring my predecessors
or passing on the fruits of my research.
I only did it
so that I could become special.
I hate to tell you,
but I burned all the old materials.
The treatise you confiscated
during my arrest
is all that is left
of the heliocentric theory.
I don't mean to pour cold water
on your ten-year endeavor,
but the case is solved.
You have no role to play.
That's why torturing Oczy
is a waste of time.
Now that's an anticlimactic reply.
Yes. But it's the truth.
Moving on, what I'd like to discuss
is whether heliocentrism
really is blasphemy--
My, my.
You must really take us for fools.
I may have been negligent,
but I've still been working every day.
And in doing so, I've learned
how to spot the face of a liar.
Were there any
logical inconsistencies in what I said?
Your story makes sense.
But what I focus on is emotions.
They reveal truth more than reason does.
And the emotions
my eyes perceived from you
tell me that you're hiding something.
That's baseless speculation.
If that's the case...
let's find the basis.
You began to draw
letting out a small sigh
it felt so big.
From the window
rippled beams of light
bounced off your profile.
My body is a gathering of rain
Your fingers are spring's sunlight
filtering through the trees.
The shadows of
ink splashed on paper
depict our profiles.
I had a long dream,
We were in a hot air balloon.
I hope, someone far away
mistook it for the moon.
When I saw the sea,
my soul leapt violently.
You were captivated by the horizon.